Guide to the Ernest Amatniek Papers ALBA.309
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Ernest Amatniek Papers
1929-2005
1937-1996
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Amatniek, Ernest
Amatniek, Kathie
Amatniek, Joan Cindy
ALBA.309
5.92 Linear Feet in 3 manuscript boxes, 1 small flat box, 1 serial flat box, and 2 folders in a shared oversize flat box
Ernest Amatniek (1915-2005) was born in Estonia and emigrated to the United States in 1929. In February 1937, Amatniek joined and served with the XV International Brigade in the signal corps that fought for the Spanish Republic in the Spanish Civil War. The Ernest Amatniek Papers contain materials related to Amatniek's service with the International Brigade through his collection of publications, correspondence, and military communications from the late 1930s. Photographs from this collection include images of Amatniek fighting in Spain and recovering in a military hospital; friends and co-workers; and in later years, veteran marching parades. This collection also includes material related to Amatniek's organized trips to Spain for the 50th and 60th anniversary celebrations of the International Brigade veterans. Press clippings and ephemera from a 1997 exhibition in Tampa, Florida commemorate the support for the Spanish Republic within Florida's Spanish communities during the 1930s. Amatniek's 2005 obituary as well as memorial material are also in this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Joan Cindy Amatniek and Kathie Amatniek in April 2019. The accession number associated with this gift is 2019.065.
Appraisal
The following were removed from the collection: Issues of Bombs over Barcelona, and Aeronáotica (heavy damage); Spanish museum brochures/store catalog; and New York Times clippings.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged in chronological order.
Biographical Note
Ernest Amatniek was born in 1915 in Estonia and emigrated to the United States in 1929. Amatniek attended James Monroe High School in the Bronx and later the City College of New York where he studied electrical engineering. In February 1937, Amatniek joined and served with the XV International Brigade Transmissiones Squad fighting for the Spanish Republic in the Spanish Civil War. Amatniek passed away in April 2005 at the age of 90 in Bucks County, Pennsylvania.
Scope and Contents
The Ernest Amatniek Papers contain materials created and collected by Ernest Amatniek documenting his experiences serving with the International Brigades during the Spanish Civil War. The collection includes political booklets/pamphlets, travel documentation, and military communications related to Amatniek's service in Spain in the late 1930s. His collected publications include The Volunteer for Liberty, La Traca, Photo-History, and La Medicina Catalana. In this collection is a selection of typed letters from Amatniek to friends and family which were reproduced and distributed, describing his experiences in Spain from 1937 to 1938. Photographs in the collection include images of Amatniek and others living and fighting in Spain, and later his daily life as a combat casualty recovering from a leg wound in a military hospital in 1938. This collection also includes photographs of Amatniek with friends and co-workers, as well as participating in Veteran parades after returning to the United States. Amatniek's 50th and 60th veteran anniversary trips back to Spain in 1986 and 1996 are documented in this collection through photographs, schedules, correspondence, and ephemera. Promotional material and correspondence related to a 1997 exhibition Amatniek attended in Tampa, Florida illustrates the support for the Spanish Republic within communities in Florida during the 1930s. This collection also includes Amatniek's 2005 obituary and later tributes.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- International brigades.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Photographs.; Fliers (printed matter); Correspondence.; Articles.; Serials (publications); Amatniek, Kathie; Amatniek, Joan Cindy; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade
- Latvian Vocational School Student ID Card, September 5, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographs -- Amatniek and Friends, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Spanish Language Children's Books, circa 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 3)
- España?, February 1933 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Booklets and Pamphlets on the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1938 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
- La Traca, circa 1936-1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- 10 Litografias Por Piiyol, February 1937 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Estudios, April 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Photo-History, April, October-December 1937 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- La Fesomia Geográfica de Catalunya, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Letters from Amatniek to Friends, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Spanish Military-Related Memos / Letters to Amatniek, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Democracia Española, December 30, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- La Medicina Catalana, December 1937 - January 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Mundo Gráfico, January 5, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- The Volunteer for Liberty, February, April, September-December 1938, November 1946 (Box 2, Folder 6, Box 4, Folder 7-8)
- News of Spain, March 1938 - February 1939 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
- Bulletin of Information for C.N.T -- A.I.T -- F.A.I., May 21, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Partido Comunista de Espana Boletin Informacion (English Edition), May 26, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- I.W.M.A. (International Working-Men's Association) Press Service, May 30, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- English-Spanish Grammar Book Compiled by The Volunteer for Liberty, June 1938 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Tiempos Nuevos, July, September 1938 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Among Friends, Winter 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Amatniek Passport and Other Travel-Related Documents, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Labor Union Support Letter to Amatniek, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Booklets Containing Biographies of Americans Killed While Fighting in Spanish Civil War, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Photographs -- Amatniek with Others in Spain Fighting and Recovering from Wound in Hospital, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Booklets with Articles and Stories Written on the Spanish Civil War, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- L'Esquella de La Torratxa, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Socorro Rojo Internacional International Brigade Recruitment Flier / Poster, 1938 (Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 15)
- Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade -- Membership Card, Certificates, 1938-1940 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Photographs -- Amatniek Picketing, Office Friends, Friend Group Posing, 1938, circa 1940s (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Booklets on Spain and the War, 1942-1949 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Photographs -- Amatniek and Others on Trip, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Informational Brochures on Anniversary Tours in Soviet Union, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- International Brigade Veterans 50th Anniversary Reunion Trip to Spain and Events, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 12, Box 4, Box 5, Folder 1)
- International Brigade Veterans 60th Anniversary Reunion Trip to Spain and Related, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 1-2, Box 4, Folder 13, Box 5, Folder 2-7)
- Booklets on Albanian International Brigade Veterans, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Spanish Civil War Exhibitions and Events in Tampa, Florida, 1997, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 4, Box 5, Folder 8)
- Ernest Amatniek Obituaries and Tributes, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Socorro Rojo de España Poster, Undated (Box Shared Tamiment 171, Folder 16)
- Aurora Roja! -- Song Sheet Music, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Calderilla Comic Book, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
- 10 Muertos Gloriosos -- Propaganda Offices of C.N.T. - F.A.I. - JJ.LL., Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)